本节我们要看我们的第一个密钥交换协议，不借助可信任第三方
In this segment we're going to look at our first key exchange protocol without a trusted third party.
这里的通常设定是，我们有我们的朋友Alice和Bob
So the settings are, we have our friends Alice and Bob as usual.
这两朋友之前从未见面，但他们想生成一个共享密钥
And these friends have never met before but somehow they want to generate a shared key.
那么他们互相发送信息
So what they're going to do is they're going to send messages to one another, back and forth.
这次没有可信任第三方可以和他们交流了
And this time there is no trusted third party that they can communicate with.
在协议的最后，他们必须获得某个双方都知道的共享密钥
And at the end of this protocol, somehow they should have a shared key that they both know.
所以有个双方都知道的密钥k
So there's a secret key k that they both know.
窃听通信流量的攻击者绝对无法得知这个密钥k是什么
But an eavesdropper who listens in on this traffic has absolutely no idea what this secret key k is.
目前我们只关心监听会话的攻击者
For now we're just going to worry about attackers that only eavesdrop on the conversation.
换句话说，我们不允许任何对通信流量的篡改
In other words, we don't allow any tampering with traffic.
我们只允许窃听，而且窃听者
All we allow is just eavesdropping, and yet eavesdroppers should
不应该知道密钥k是什么
have no idea what the secret key k is.
在这些设定下，我们将看到很多密钥交换协议
So we're going to look at a number of key exchange protocols in these settings.
当攻击者仅仅是窃听会话时
Namely, when the attacker is only eavesdropping on the conversation
不能改变流量。我们将看到三个协议来达到这一目标
but cannot change traffic. And we're going to see three protocols that achieve this goal.
本节的第一个问题是
And the first question, though, for this segment, is
这点能使用对称密码学做到吗？
"Can this be done only using symmetric crypto?"
可不可以只使用分组密码或哈希函数
So can this only be done using block ciphers or hash functions, or any of the tools
或是只使用我们前面四周所见的任何技术？
that we've seen in the last four weeks?
令人惊奇的是，答案是肯定的，事实上我们可以进行密钥交换
And so very surprisingly, the answer is "Yes", in fact we can do key exchange
只使用分组密码或哈希函数，不借助可信任第三方
just using block ciphers or hash functions without a trusted third party
但是很不幸，得到的协议非常低效，在实际中从未被使用
but unfortunately the resulting protocols are very inefficient and are actually never used in practice.
不过，这些协议特别简单，所以我想告诉大家它们是如何工作的
Nevertheless, these are very simple protocols and so I want to show you how they work,
然后我们再看更为有效的协议，也就是这两周的内容
and then we'll move on to the more efficient protocols that we'll discuss this week and the next.
我想给大家展示的简单协议叫做Merkle谜题协议
So the simple protocol I want to show you what's called a Merkle Puzzles protocol.
这个协议由Ralph Merkle于1974年发明，当时他还在读本科
This protocol was invented by Ralph Merkle back in 1974 when he was just an undergraduate.
有趣的是，他发明这个协议，作为他选的研习课的一部分
Interestingly, he invented this protocol as part of a seminar that he took,
很明显他的教授不是很理解这一贡献的重要性
but apparently the professor didn't quite understand the significance of the contribution
因此，Ralph Merkle毕业后
and as a result Ralph Merkle actually graduated and then moved
去了斯坦福大学，成为了Marty Hellman的学生
to Stanford where he became Marty Hellman's student
从那以后，他们为公钥密码学做了很多贡献
and they've done a lot of good things in public-key cryptography since then.
那么我来告诉大家Merkle谜题的工作过程
So let me show you how Merkle Puzzles work.
这个协议的主要工具叫做一个"谜题"
The main tool for this protocol is what's called a "puzzle"
我来解释这个谜题的意思
and let me explain what I mean by a puzzle.
谜题是指难解的问题，但通过努力还是可以解出的
A puzzle is a problem that's difficult to solve, but can be solved with some effort.
换句话说，如果大家专心研究，是可以解出来的
In other words, if you really put your mind to it you can solve it.
我来给个例子
So let me give an example.
假设我们有一个对称密码，使用128位的密钥
Suppose we have a symmetric cipher that uses keys that are 128 bits long
以AES为例
So just think of AES for example.
假设我选择的AES密钥的前96位都是0
And suppose what I do is a choose an AES key such that the first 96 bits are all 0
只有剩下的32位是非零的，并随机选取的
and only the remaining 32 bits are non-zero and just chosen at random.
128位密钥中只有32位是随机的。其他都是0
Ok, so only 32 bits of this 128-bit key are random. The rest are all 0.
现在我加密一段固定的明文，比如说
And now what I do is I encrypt a fixed plaintext, for example,
加密明文"message"，使用128位密钥，大部分位都是0
simply the plaintext "message" using this 128-bit key that happens to be mostly 0.
加密的结果叫做"谜题"
The result is what I would call a "puzzle".
我称之为谜题，是因为其实不难找到
The reason I call it a puzzle is because it's actually not that hard to find
密钥P，只需要尝试所有2的32次方种可能性
the secret key P simply by trying all 2-to-the-32 possibilities.
记住前96位都是0，所以只需要试2的32次方个可能的密钥
Remember the first 96 bits are all 0, there are only 2-to-the-32 possible keys to try.
尝试用每个密钥去解密这个谜题，看看是否得到明文"message"
And for each key we'll try to decrypt this puzzle and see if we get the plaintext "message".
如果是的话，我们就知道了已经发现了正确的答案P
If so, we know that we've recovered the right solution, P.
最多2的32次方次尝试，我们就可以解出这个谜题
So within 2-to-the-32 work, we can actually solve this puzzle.
给定谜题(P)，我们可以找到P
Namely, we can find P just given puzzle (P).
那么协议的工作方式如下：
So the way this is going to work is as follows:
Alice开始时生成大量的谜题
Alice is going to start by generating a large number of puzzles.
特别地，她将生成2的32次方个不同的谜题
In particular, she's going to generate 2-to-the-32 different puzzles.
对于每个谜题，她生成的方法如下：
Now each of these puzzles, the way she generates it is as follows:
她会选择一个32位随机谜题P_i
What' she'll do is she'll choose a 32-bit random puzzle P-i,
这里的i从1遍历到2的32次方
she does this for i = 1 to 2-to-the-32
然后她再选择两个值x_i和k_i
and then she's going to choose two more values, x-i and k-i that
每个128位
happen to be 128-bits each.
现在她会使用谜题P_i作为一个AES密钥
Now what she'll do is she'll use the puzzle P-i as an AES secret key.
她会产生128位密钥，其中前96位都是0
So she'll create 128-bit key where 96 of the bits are set to 0.
只有最低32位是随机的
And only the 32 least significant bits happen to be random.
所以这个密钥的熵是32位，如果大家算一下
So this is a key that only has 32 bits of entropy, if you like,
(H(M)=-\sum p_i \log p_i，p_i表示各字符串出现概率)
只有2的32次方个密钥
and there are only 2-to-the-32 such keys.
现在她要使用这个密钥加密的明文
Now the plaintext that she'll encrypt using this key
是我写在这里的信息
is this message that I wrote over here.
这个明文以"Puzzle"开头
Basically it's starts off with the word "Puzzle".
谜题被表示为x_i
That puzzle is identified by the identifier x-i,
正好是128位
which happens to be 128 bits.
我们在x_i后面附上k_i
And to that we concatenate a value k-i which also happens
k_i正好也是128位
to be 128 bits.
那么她对所有的2的32次方个谜题都这么做
So she does this for all 2-to-the-32 puzzles, and as a result
于是她得到了2的32次方个不同的谜题
she gets 2-to-the-32 different puzzles.
然后她把这2的32次方个谜题发送给Bob
She then goes ahead and sends these 2-to-the-32 puzzles to Bob.
那Bob做什么呢？
So what does Bob do?
Bob接收了这如同洪水般的2的32次方个不同谜题
Well Bob receives this flood of 2-to-the-32 different puzzles.
他只选择其中一个
He's just going to choose one of them.
他不需要记住所有的谜题
He doesn't even have to remember any of them.
他只需要随机地忽略大部分谜题
He just randomly lets most of them go by.
只选择其中的一个谜题
And he happens to choose one of them.
比如说他选择了谜题j
Let's say he chose puzzle number "j".
他花了2的32次方的时间来解决这个谜题
Then he spends time 2-to-the-32 and solves this puzzle.
解决这个谜题是什么意思？
Well what does it mean to solve this puzzle?
他要尝试所有可能的P_i
He's going to try all possible values of P-i.
他要解密他选择的谜题
He's going to decrypt the puzzle that he chose, and
他要检查明文的前面部分
he's going to check whether the first part of the plaintext starts
是否以"Puzzle"开头
with the word puzzle.
如果确实是这样，Bob就知道了他正确地解决了这个谜题
And if it does, he knows that he's correctly solved that puzzle,
然后他就获得了嵌在谜题里的数据
and he basically obtains the data embedded in the puzzle
x_j和k_j
namely, x-j and k-j.
记得x_j是这个谜题的标记
Remember x-j is this value that identifies the puzzle
k_j是他们要使用的秘密信息
and k-j is going to be a secret that they use.
现在他已经解决了这个谜题--他知道了如何正确地解决这个谜题
So now he's solved the puzzle -- he knows that he's solved the puzzle correctly
他获得了这个x_j和k_j
and he obtained this x-j and k-j.
他会把x_j发送给Alice
What he'll do is he'll send x-j back to Alice
只发送x_j的值。k_j他自己保留，作为秘密
-- just the value of x-j. k-j he keeps for himself, and keeps it a secret.
然后Alice查找他的谜题数据库
And then Alice is simply going to lookup in her database
她会查到谜题x_j
of puzzles, she's going to lookup puzzle number x-j,
就知道了Bob选择的密钥k_j
and then she knows Bob chose the key k-j.
现在他们就有了这个共享密钥
And now they have this shared key.
那么k_j就是这个共享密钥，可以被用来保证他们之间的安全通信
So k-j is going to be the shared key they that use to communicate securely with one another.
以图表的形式，这个协议如下工作：
So in a diagram the way this protocol works is as follows:
开始时Alice发送2的32次方个谜题给Bob
Alice starts off by sending 2-to-the-32 puzzles to Bob.
那么我们可以推广这个说法，比如说她发送n个谜题给Bob
So we can generalize this. Let's say that she says n puzzles to Bob.
每个谜题需要花正比于n的时间来解决
And let's say that each puzzle takes work proportional to n to solve.
Bob解决其中一个谜题
Bob solves one of these puzzles,
然后把x_j发送给Alice
and then he sends back x-j to Alice.
目前双方都花了时间n
So far each one of them has spent work n.
然后Alice查看谜题x_j
And then Alice basically looks up puzzle x-j
还原出对应于谜题的密钥
and recovers the key that corresponds to this puzzle.
因此现在双方有了一个共享密钥
And as a result both of them now have a shared key
他们可以使用这个密钥来相互交流
that they can use to communicate with one another.
我们来看他们所做的工作
Ok so let's look at the work they did.
Alice必须准备n个谜题
So the work that Alice did is that she had to prepare n puzzles.
准备谜题花掉固定长的时间
Well, preparing the puzzle takes constant time.
她必须准备n个谜题，她的工作是O(n)的
She had to prepare n puzzles, so her work is roughly order n.
Bob选择一个谜题并解决
Bob chose one puzzle and solved it, so his work
所以他的工作是与n成正比的。与n成线性
is also proportional to order n. So linear in n.
我们看窃听者怎么办
Let's see what the eavesdropper has to do.
可怜的窃听者看着n个谜题过去了
Well the poor eavesdropper sees these n puzzles go by
然后他看到Bob返回了一个x_j
and then he sees this x-j come back.
攻击者并不知道Bob解的是哪个谜题
And he doesn't really know which puzzle Bob actually solved.
他看到的只是谜题中的随机值
All he sees is this random value inside of the puzzle.
为了破解这个协议，窃听者会
And so to break this protocol, the eavesdropper would
解决所有的谜题，直到他找到正确的谜题
actually have to solve all puzzles until he finds the right puzzle
里面有x_j，那么攻击者就会还原k_j
that has the value x-j in it, and then he will recover k-j.
我给大家的问题是，"攻击者要做多少工作？"
So my question to you is, "What is the attacker's work?"
攻击者必须做多少工作
How much work did the eavesdropper have to spend
才能破解这个协议？
in order to break this protocol.
答案当然是O(n^2)
So the answer is, of course, order n-squared.
n平方的时间
You know, quadratic time in n.
他必须解决n个谜题。每个谜题花掉时间n
He had to solve n puzzles. Each puzzle takes time n to solve.
因此他必须花掉时间n^2
And as a result he had to spend time order n-squared.
在我们的例子中，我们说过有2的32次方个谜题
In our example we said that there were 2-to-the-32 puzzles
每个谜题需要2的32次方的时间来解决
and each one took 2-to-the-32 time to solve,
所以总的来看，攻击者需要做2的64次方步工作
so overall the attacker's work is roughly 2-to-the-64 steps.
大家可以看到这个协议的问题了
So you can see the problem with this protocol.
首先，参与者Alice和Bob自己
First of all, the participants Alice and Bob had to do quite
需要做大量的工作
a bit of work themselves.
想一想，Alice必须发送
If you think about it, Alice basically had to send
2的32次方个谜题给Bob
2-to-the-32 puzzles to Bob.
她必须发很多GB的数据给Bob
That's many, many gigabytes that she had to send to Bob.
比如16GB或32GB，取决于谜题的大小
Like 16 or 32 gigabytes, depending on how big each puzzle is.
Bob必须花2的32次方的时间，来解决其中的一个谜题
Bob had to spend time 2-to-the-32 to solve one of these puzzles.
这大概也会花几秒钟
That would take a few seconds, too.
那么他们获得的所有的安全性在于
But then, all the security they got is that the attacker
攻击者可以在2的64次方的时间内破解这一协议
can break this protocol in time 2-to-the-64.
2的64次方依然不能被认为是安全的
So 2-to-the-64 is still not considered particularly secure.
因此，如果攻击者真想
As a result, the attacker, really, if he really wanted
破解这个协议，他是可以的
to break this protocol, he could.
那么为了让这个协议安全，参与双方必须
So to make this secure, the participants would have to
增加参数n
increase the parameter n.
他们必须发送，比如说，2的64次方个谜题
And they would have to send, say, 2-to-the-64
给对方，然后花2的64次方的时间
puzzles to one another, and then spend time 2-to-the-64
去解决这个谜题，那么攻击者的工作
to solve each puzzle, and then the attacker's work
将是2的128次方，可认为是安全的了
would be 2-to-the-128, which is considered secure.
但是参与者花了2的64次方的时间
But having the participants spend time 2-to-the-64 to
来建立一个安全的会话，对每个参与者来说
set up a secure session is a little bit too much
有点吃力了
to ask each of these participants.
所以这就是为什么这个协议不实用
So this is why this protocol is not particularly used in practice.
不过这里有一个很好的想法
But nevertheless there's a really nice idea here
攻击者必须花线性的时间
in that the participants had to spend linear time,
而攻击者必须花平方的时间
whereas the attacker had to spend quadratic time.
这就有一个"平方鸿沟"
So there's a "quadratic gap" between the amount of
横亘在参与者与攻击者的工作之间
work that the participants had to do, versus what the attacker
当攻击者想破解这个协议
had to do to break the protocol.
那么一个很自然的问题是，我们能否做得更好？
So a natural question is, "Can we actually do better
只使用对称密码，做得比平方鸿沟更好呢？
than a quadratic gap, just using symmetric ciphers?"
换句话说，使用我们前面四个礼拜
In other words, just using tools
在本课程中见过的技术
that we developed in the first four weeks of the class.
答案是未知的
And the answer really is that this is unknown.
我们不知道平方鸿沟是否是我们所能做到的最好的结果
We don't know whether a quadratic gap is the best that we can do.
大家可以试着想一想
You might even try to think about this a bit.
如何使用AES或SHA-256来进行密钥交换
How would you use AES or SHA-256 to do key exchange
可以获得比平方鸿沟更好的结果？
that achieves better than a quadratic gap.
不过我可以告诉大家，我们相信
But I can tell you that we believe that quadratic
平方鸿沟是我们所能做到的最好的了
is the best we can do.
这里甚至还有一些负面的结果
And there are even some negative results along those lines.
不严格地说，有一个结果说
So roughly speaking, there is a result that says
事实上，如果我们把分组密码或哈希函数
that, in fact, if we treat the block cipher or the hash function
当作黑盒神谕来使用，换句话说
that we use as a black box oracle -- in other words
参与者只能询问分组密码
all the participants can do is just query the block cipher
或询问哈希函数在特定点的值
or query the hash function at certain points
并获得结果，如果这些是参与者所能做的全部
and receive the results -- if that's all they're allowed to do,
换句话说，参与者不能实际使用
in other words, they're not allowed to actually use the implementation
分组密码或哈希函数的实现
of the cipher, or the hash function, then in fact
那么事实上有一个结果告诉我们，如果参与者只能
there is a result that says that if the participants only query
询问分组密码在n个点的值，那么总有一个攻击
the block cipher at n points, there will always be an attack
运行在n平方的时间里
that runs in time n-squared.
这就是说，如果你只能使用
So again this suggests that if all you do is use
分组密码作为一个黑盒进行询问
the block cipher as a black box that you query,
那么无论交换什么密钥
then whatever key exchange you come up with,
这个密钥交换总有一个平方时间的攻击
there will always be a quadratic attack on this key exchange.
事实上，在本章结束时，我指出这篇论文
And, in fact, at the end of this module, I point to this
最近的一篇2009年的论文
paper -- it's a fairly recent paper from 2009 -- that shows
证明了平方是我们能做的最好的
that quadratic is best we can do.
如果大家想了解更多的关于这种不可能性的结果
If you want to read more about this impossibility result
去读这篇文章吧
you know, go ahead and take a look at this paper.
这篇论文可读性强，大家应该能理解它
It's actually a very readable paper, and you should be able to understand it.
那么问题是接下来怎么办？
And so the question is what to do next.
我们有点困住了
So now we're kind of stuck.
我们说过用分组密码，我们不能
We said that with block ciphers, we really can't do
做得比平方鸿沟更好
better than a quadratic gap.
那我们怎么办？
And so what do we do?
那么这就是公钥密码学的起点
So this was kind of the starting point of public-key cryptography.
我们发现，我们需要
And the realization is that we need more than just
比通用分组密码和哈希函数更多的技术
generic block ciphers and generic hash functions.
我们实际上需要具备非常特殊性质的函数
We actually need functions that have very, very special properties.
为了构建这些函数，我们实际上必须依赖于某些代数
And to build these functions, we actually have to rely on some algebra.
下面几节我们看
So in the next few segments we're going to look
一些代数机制，然后我们看
at some algebraic constructions and then we'll see
如何使用它们来进行密钥交换
how to use those for key exchange and for
以及公钥密码学里的许多其他技术
many other things in public-key cryptography.